Guide to the Sparrow Papers MSS.096
Fales Library and Special Collections
Sparrow Papers
1970-2012
Fales Library and Special Collections
Sparrow, (American poet)
MSS.096
5.5 Linear Feet in 5 boxes and 1 manuscript box
Sparrow is a longtime poet/activist/musician of the Lower East Side of Manhattan and a member of the literary group, the Unbearables. He has published several chapbooks of poetry in collaboration with the St. Mark's Poetry Project and other poetry organizations, and he has served as the editor for the literary journal Big Fish. He has been published in The New Yorker, as well as The Quarterly, and The New York Times. The Sparrow Papers are a diverse collection of materials including manuscripts, notes, journals, travelogues, handwritten signs, and periodicals.
Provenance
This collection was acquired by purchase.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open without restrictions.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author heading.
The files are grouped into four series.
Missing Title
Series I: Manuscripts
Series II: Journals/Travelogues
Series III: Personal
Series IV: Books/Periodicals
Biographical Note
Sparrow is a longtime poet/activist of the Lower East Side of Manhattan. He has published several chapbooks of poetry in collaboration with the St. Mark's Poetry Project and other poetry organizations, and he has served as the editor for the literary journal Big Fish. He gained notoriety in 1995 by picketing The New Yorker, holding a sign that read, "My poetry is as bad as yours." Since then, he has been published in that magazine as well as The Quarterly and The New York Times. In 1996, he ran for president and published the book Republican Like Me: A Diary of My Presidential Campaign about his experiences. In addition to his work as a poet, Sparrow is a member of the Unbearables (along with Ron Kolm, Richard Kostelanetz, and Rob Witz), and the founder of the East Village Militia and the One Size Fits All Movement. He is also a member of the musical group Foamola.
Related Material at the Fales Library and Special Collections
For more information see the Ron Kolm Papers, the Richard Kostelanetz Papers, and the Rob Witz Papers in Fales Library.
Scope and Content Note
The Sparrow Papers are a diverse collection of materials including manuscripts, notes, journals, travelogues, handwritten signs, and periodicals.
The manuscripts are in the form of typescripts (some with corrections) or handwritten notes, most pertaining to an unidentified novel and are labeled as such. The collection also includes journals and travelogues detailing Sparrow's travels and including notes and drafts of original poetry and fiction. Sparrow's other the personal files in the collection include articles, correspondence, information on Foamola, the New Yorker occupation, and the East Village Militia, and miscellaneous travel documents. The published material within the collection is from Sparrow's collection of periodicals, books, and chapbooks. Published books and chapbooks written by Sparrow have been catalogued and are located within the downtown collection at Fales Library.
Poets, American -- 20th century.; Posters.; Magazines (Periodicals); Authors, American -- 20th century.; New York (N.Y.).; Journals (accounts); American literature -- 20th century.; Literature, Experimental.; Artists and community -- United States; Manuscripts for publication.; Avant-garde (Aesthetics); Travelers' writings; Unbearables (Literary group)
- Series I: Manuscripts, Undated; 94713
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I contains the manuscript files of Sparrow's poetry and fiction, most of which are in the form of typescripts (some with corrections) or handwritten notes. A large number of these files are manuscript fragments pertaining to an unidentified novel and are labeled as such. The author's original grouping of manuscript fragments is maintained.
  - Born Too Young: A Pilgrimage Diary-computer printout, undated; 94758 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Born Too Young: A Pilgrimage Diary-computer printout, undated; 94757 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Born Too Young: A Pilgrimage Diary-typescript, pp. 1-182, undated; 94756 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Born Too Young: A Pilgrimage Diary-typescript, pp. 183-326, undated; 94755 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Born Too Young: A Pilgrimage Diary-typescript, pp. 327-480, undated; 94754 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Born Too Young: A Pilgrimage Diary-typescript, undated; 94753 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Born Too Young: A Pilgrimage Diary-typescript, undated; 94752 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Born Too Young: A Pilgrimage Diary-typescript submitted to Pantheon Books, pp., undated; 94751 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Born Too Young: A Pilgrimage Diary-typescript submitted to Pantheon Books, pp. 161-370, undated; 94750 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Born Too Young: A Pilgrimage Diary-typescript submitted to Pantheon Books, pp. 371-480, undated; 94749 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Born Too Young: A Pilgrimage Diary-typescript with corrections, pp. 161-239, 1-83, undated; 94748 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Born Too Young: A Pilgrimage Diary-typescript with corrections, pp. 1-160, undated; 94747 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, handwritten poems, notes, and short works, undated; 94746 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - New Yorker: Poems written to the New Yorker during occupation of offices, undated; 94745 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Novel: Unidentified-handwritten notes, undated; 94744 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Novel: Unidentified-handwritten notes, undated; 94743 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Novel: Unidentified-handwritten notes, undated; 94742 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Novel: Unidentified-handwritten notes, undated; 94741 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Novel: Unidentified-handwritten notes, undated; 94740 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Novel: Unidentified-handwritten notes, undated; 94739 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Novel: Unidentified-handwritten notes, undated; 94738 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Novel: Unidentified-handwritten notes, undated; 94737 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Novel: Unidentified-handwritten notes, undated; 94736 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Novel: Unidentified-handwritten notes, undated; 94735 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Novel: Unidentified-handwritten notes, undated; 94734 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Novel: Unidentified-typescript with corrections, undated; 94733 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Novel: Unidentified-typescript with corrections, undated; 94732 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Novel: Unidentified-typescript with corrections, undated; 94731 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Novel: Unidentified-typescript with corrections, undated; 94730 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Novel: Unidentified-typescript with corrections, undated; 94729 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Novel: Unidentified-typescript with corrections, undated; 94728 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Novel: Unidentified-typescript with corrections, undated; 94727 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Novel: Unidentified-typescript with corrections, undated; 94726 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Novel: Unidentified-typescript with corrections, undated; 94725 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - One Size Fits All Movement-poems, undated; 94724 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Poems, undated; 94723 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Power Poetry, undated; 94722 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Sparrow for Prez, undated; 94721 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Unidentified, handwritten fragments, undated; 94720 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Unidentified, handwritten notes, undated; 94719 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Unidentified, handwritten notes, undated; 94718 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Unidentified, handwritten notes, undated; 94717 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Unidentified typescript with corrections, undated; 94716 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Uptown Dispatches, pp. 1-109, undated; 94715 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Uptown Dispatches, pp. 110-234, undated; 94714 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Series II: Journals/Travelogues, Undated; 94693
  Series II contains journals and travelogues detailing Sparrow's journeys in Europe and India. Interspersed with the autobiographical information in these journals are notes and drafts of original poetry and fiction.
  - Journals, undated; 94712 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Journals, undated; 94711 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Journals, undated; 94710 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Journals, undated; 94709 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Journals, undated; 94708 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Journals, undated; 94707 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Journals, undated; 94706 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Journals, undated; 94705 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Journals, undated; 94704 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Journals, undated; 94703 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Journals, undated; 94702 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Journals, undated; 94701 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Journals, undated; 94700 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Journals, undated; 94699 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Journals, undated; 94698 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Journals, undated; 94697 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Journals, undated; 94696 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Journals, undated; 94695 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Journals, undated; 94694 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Series III: Personal, Undated, 1991-2012; 94679
  Series III contains the personal files, which include articles, correspondence, information on Foamola, the New Yorker occupation, and the East Village Militia, and miscellaneous travel documents.
  - Articles-"Light In Our Catskills, A Sparrow." The Mountain Eagle, 7/17/1997, 94692 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Articles-Sparrow. Garbage In Mind. Whole Earth Review, Spring 1991, 94691 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Articles-Sparrow. Tomorrow's News, undated; 94690 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Calendar, undated; 94689 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Cartoons, drawings, and original artwork, undated; 94688 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, undated; 94687 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - The East Village Militia, undated; 94686 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Foamola signs (musical group with Sparrow), undated; 94685 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Hitchhiking signs indicating city destinations, undated; 94684 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - New Yorker: Signs protesting the New Yorker, undated; 94683 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Sherwin, Richard E. A Strange Courage-manuscript submitted to Sparrow, undated; 94682 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Topp, Mike materials, undated; 94681 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Travel, undated; 94680 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Notes - mixed, Undated; 216011 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Notes - mixed, Undated; 216012 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Notes - mixed, Undated; 216013 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Notes - mixed, Undated; 216014 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - The True Story of How I Went Punk, Crumbs From My Cabana, drawings, drafts, notes., 2000-2012 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
- Series IV: Books/Periodicals, 1988-1995; 94655
  Series IV contains Sparrow's collection of periodicals, books, and chapbooks. Published books and chapbooks written by Sparrow have been catalogued and are located within the downtown collection at Fales Library.
  - Appearances, vol. 22, undated; 94678 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Big Fish: Council of All Beings Issue, undated; 94677 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - The 11th Street Russe, vol. 1, no. 0, undated; 94676 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Environs, undated; 94675 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Gandhabba, no. 4, 5, undated; 94674 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Mahamatsya, undated; 94673 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Mr. Puke Reviews, no. 10, Sept. 1995, 94672 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - National Poetry Magazine of the Lower East Side, vol. 3, no. 2, Summer 1988, 1998; 94671 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - The Poetry Project, no. 127, Feb. /Mar. 1988, 94670 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Sam'Gram, vol. 3, no. 1, undated; 94669 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Soon 3, undated; 94668 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Sparrow. Denver. 1991, undated; 94667 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - The Sun, issues 109, 112, 113, 120, 126, 128, undated; 94666 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - The Sun, issues 130, 136, 145, 149, 154, 162, undated; 94665 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - The Sun, issues 164-66, 171, 176, 178, undated; 94664 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - The Sun, issues 181-186, undated; 94663 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - The Sun, issues 187-192, undated; 94662 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - The Sun, issues 193, 194, 196-199, undated; 94661 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - The Sun, issues 200, 206, 210, 217, 231, 233, undated; 94660 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Tamarind, undated; 94659 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Taylor, Anique. Poems., undated; 94658 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Unidentified Zine, undated; 94657 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Wilson, Blair and Sparrow. "That's Cool. " [19]92., 94656 (Box 4, Folder 39)